Guide to the Paper Tiger Television Archive, ca. 1981-2014 MSS.276
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series VII: Video recordings
  - Subseries A: PTTV - Broadcast Videotapes
    - Murray Bookchin Reads Time - Master, January 27, 1982 (Box 54, Media ID: 276.0025)
      Murray Bookchin gives a critical reading of Time magazine by tackling the pacification of world news through their pages. He claims that "Time obliterates time" as the past, present, and future of America is blurred week-by-week. By condensing all events into consumable chunks, Time creates a monotonous layout of our history, one that captures no true feeling or sense of perspective.
    - Brian Winston Reads TV Guide - dub from Beta master dubmaster, 1982 (Box 54, Media ID: 276.0026)
      Brian Winston Reads TV Guide: Journal of the Wasteland
      Brian Winston considers the contradiction between TV Guide's critique of television and its actual mission to bolster the television industry. He unveils the business dealings of TV Guide owner Walter Annenberg, examines featured stories, and critiques the cover of the best-selling magazine in the country.
      1982 TRT: 28 minutes #21
    - Brian Winston Reads TV Guide - Master, 1982 (Box 54, Media ID: 276.0027)
      Brian Winston considers the contradiction between TV Guide's critique of television and its actual mission to bolster the television industry. He unveils the business dealings of TV Guide owner Walter Annenberg, examines featured stories and critiques the cover of the best-selling magazine in the country.
    - Brian Winston Reads TV Guide - Master, April 28, 1982 (Box 54, Media ID: 276.0028)
    - Brian Winston Reads TV News - 2nd Master, 1983 (Box 54, Media ID: 276.0029)
      Brian Winston Reads the TV News: Live and on Tape
      This show features the analysis of television network news by Brian Winston. Winston looks at the news as a unique institution, governed by its own conventions and constraints and questions how the news use pictures, body language, narrative, and dream logic. He investigates the idea that the nightly news is "holding the nation together" is as well as other themes such as "journalistic intervention" and state sponsored propaganda.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #22
    - Brian Winston Reads TV News - Master, 1983 (Box 54, Media ID: 276.0030)
    - Bill Tabb Reads U.S. News & World Report - Master, May 26, 1982 (Box 55, Media ID: 276.0031)
      Bill Tabb Reads U.S. News and World Report: Disrobing the Economy
      Bill Tabb critiques U.S. News and World Report. He points out the publication's bias directive to aid the debilitating force of Reaganomics. As Tabb sees it, US News and World Report is no less than nationalist propaganda masquerading as objective journalism.
      1982 TRT: minute #23
    - Serafina Bathrik Reads Working Woman - Master, 1983 (Box 55, Media ID: 276.0032)
      Serafina Bathrick Reads Working Woman: Women in Grey Flannel Stifle Their Rage
      Sarafina Bathrick focuses on Working Woman magazine's editorial position, views, and messages to the emerging 1980's women in the workforce. Magazine themes, such as how to enter the "mans world" of business and "working your way up", are deconstructed by Sarafina to eventually reveal an idea of the supremacy of the male world image of success and a woeful lack of critically viewing a woman's right to work in a post-feminist world.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #24
    - Serafina Bathrik Reads Working Woman - 2nd Master, 1983 (Box 55, Media ID: 276.0033)
    - Martha Rosler Reads Vogue, 1982 / May 18, 1998 (Box 55, Media ID: 276.0034)
      Martha Rosler Reads Vogue: Wishing, Dreaming, Winning, Spending
      In using a collage based structure that focuses on impressions, personal stories, and, most provocatively, looking at Vogue's place in creating and recreating class power, Martha Roslers scrutinizes the popular fashio magazine. She also include a quick portrait of Conde Nast, the media mogul who owned Vogue and an array of other "high-style" magazines in the early 20th century. Rosler confronts the viewer with the bizarre and sexist imagery of the magazine's fashion ads; it is not difficult to see how media outlets like Vogue spread the idealization of upper class lifestyles, bringing people to a point where they seek validity in emulating such exaggerated portrayals of the wealthy. In her opinion, the magazine is targeted at middle class women, delivering a message of artificial promise and encouraging a lifestyle consumption to the average person, but at a price. By getting people to try to identify with the leisure class, and arranging the anxiety of the unobtainable into a perpetual want, the magazine and others like it are key instruments of social control. Vogue is but one symptom of a consumerism based on bodies, specifically female bodies through a male-dominated gaze, never attempting a portrayal beyond surface or object.
      Though there are many ideological and gender-based criticisms of magazines like Vogue, Rosler's show also reveals how and where the clothing products that make the imagery possible are actually produced: third-world sweatshops. A short segment on working conditions in the clothing industry highlights the warped view of the world this magazine works to instill.
      1982 TRT: 27 minutes #25
    - Oldies & Goodies, 1983 (Box 55, Media ID: 276.0035)
      Oldies and Goodies: A Paper Tiger Sampler
      A Paper Tiger's compilation, spanning the collective's first 3 years. This tape is not a regular PTTV show but rather a live show promoting an event that happened in NYC. It includes some short clips from early shows:
      #3 Herb Schiller Reads New York Times: 712 Pages of Waste; The Sunday Times, #17 Ynestra King Reads Seventeen: Selling the All-American Girl, #20 Murray Bookchin Reads Time: History as a Television Series, #21 Brian Winston Reads TV Guide: Journal of the Wasteland, #12 Natalie Didn't Drown: Joan Braderman Reads The National Enquirer,
      These clips comprise approximately 20 minutes of the entire show. The rest of the show promotes a 1983 gallery event in NYC featuring Paper Tiger productions and the work of many local video artists.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #26
    - Tuli Kupferberg Reads Sports Illustrated - Master, 1983 (Box 55, Media ID: 276.0036)
      Tuli Kupferberg Reads Sports Illustrated: In Honor of the Baseball Season
      Tuki Kupferberg reflects on the publication Sports Illustrated. He discusses the sense of generating a "contained universe" separate from conventional reality in which idealization of the human form, the sadomasochism of competition, and games in a class society are paradigms for war. Kupferberg goes on to point out the contradictory proliferation of alcohol related advertising within it's pages with it's obvious debilitating effect on motor skills and the central nervous system.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #27
    - Business Week - Master, 1983 (Box 55, Media ID: 276.0037)
      Harry Magdoff Reads: Business Week
      Harry Magdoff talks about the ruling class.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #28
    - Alex Gockburn Reads The Washington Post - Master, 1983 (Box 121, Media ID: 276.0038)
      Alex Cockburn Reads Washington Post: Clipping the Wings of the National Eagle
      Alex Cockburn talks about how the Washington Post's pronounced shift to the Right was already well underway when the show was made in 1983. Tracing a biography of the newspaper from 1963, he argues that the newspaper's scope changed to profit-making and how the Post usually has fairly conservative editorials and acts as informal agenda setter for the political class in Washington DC.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #29
    - Alex Cockburn Reads The Washington Post - New Master, 1983 (Box 55, Media ID: 276.0039)
      Cockburn talks about how the Washington Post's pronounced shift to the Right was already well underway when the show was made in 1983. Tracing a biography of the newspaper from 1963, he argues that the newspaper's scope changed to profit-making and how the Post usually has fairly conservative editorials and acts as informal agenda setter for the political class in Washington DC.
    - Archie Singham Reads Foreign Policy - Master, 1983 (Box 121, Media ID: 276.0040)
      Archie Singham Reads Foreign Policy: A Look at the Old Boys' Network
      Professor Archie Singham indicts the obscurantism and theoretical vagueness of academia as one of the primary impediments to a truly democratic media. Singham contends that issues, such as foreign policy, would weigh more heavily on the conscience of ordinary citizens if the sources of information were not hopelessly muddied by academic lingo.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #30
    - Myra Bain Reads Ebony - Master, 1983 (Box 55, Media ID: 276.0041)
      Myrna Bain Reads Ebony: Put Your Money Where Your Soul Is
      Professor Myrna Bain gives us his reading of Ebony Magazine. Started in 1945, it was made to embody the "colored answer to Life". Focusing on several issues of Ebony Magazine, Bain highlights the ways through which the magazine projects unrealistic, frivolous and misleading expectations of a "black middle class" while forgoing any coverage of important issues or political statements from local communities. Bain also points out the abundance of exploitative - advertisements, for a range of things from hair products and alcoholic drinks to, armed services recruitment and menthol cigarettes. These ads, designed to capitalize on the magazine's target audience, reinforce stereotypical assumptions about black readers, while advocating consumption and assimilation as the keys to success. Taped during a period of Reagonomic recession, the show underlines the sharp discrepancies between the glamorous lifestyle depicted in Ebony magazine and the harsh reality of unemployment and lack of public resources in many African American communities.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #31
    - Disarmament Special - Master, June 9, 1982 (Box 121, Media ID: 276.0042)
      June 12 Disarmament Special: with Joel Kovel, Nancy Cain, Susie Schneiderman and Melissa Leo
      Joel Kovel, Nancy Cain, Susie Schneiderman, and Melissa Leo take a look at disarmament. Includes scenes from the 1982 PBS-censored film, "The Dark Circle," by Chris Beaver and Judy Irvin.
      1982 TRT: 28 minutes #33
    - Joel Kovel Reads LIFE - Master, September 12, 1983 (Box 55, Media ID: 276.0043)
      Joel Kovel Reads Life: It's a New Life; Painting a Corpse
      Joel Kovel gives a critical reading of Life magazine. Kovel proposes that, from its founding by Henry Booth Luce in the 1930s until the early 1970s, Life was the voice of American cultural supremacy throught its relationship with the American government, making it a tool to shape public opinion through powerful images. Within this state of regressive corruption, Kovel says, a succession of commercial images and odes to consumer culture replaced early Life's efforts to articulate moments of lived experience through the printed image.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #35
    - Joel Kovel Reads LIFE - Master - Camera Master, 1983 (Box 121, Media ID: 276.0044)
    - Tim Haight Reads Channels - Master, 1983 (Box 55, Media ID: 276.0045)
      Tim Haight Reads: Channels
      Tim Haight gives a page by page critical reading of Channels Magazine and describes how despite being a "liberal" not-for-profit corporation, the publication was embedded in the corporate systems of the television industry. Haight points to the idea the magazine pushes an agenda of adjusting to new technologies to fit society, but neglects to acknowledge the need for change within the society itself. This contradicts the self-proclamation, which Channels makes in an ad for itself, that it is "the magazine which covers the revolution."
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #36
    - Stanley Aronowitz Reads The N.Y. Times - edited master, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0046)
      Stanley Aronowitz Reads The New York Times: A Timely Look at Labor
      Stanley Aronowitz takes a critical look at the New York Times by briefly explaining the social history of the paper and deconstructing the format and biases of the various sections. Arguing that each section is a social and cultural commentary targeted to a specific audience, Aronowitz points out the gendered notions of the *Sports* section on Mondays and the *Home* section on Thursdays. He suggests that despite its non-tabloid format, the content and presentation of the newspaper parallels TV and magazines, making it no longer a real genuine newspaper but a magazine full of advertisement and opinions. In the last section Aronowitz highlights the New York Times inability to do systematic coverage of significant national news stories, such as the pilot strike in October of 1983.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #37
    - Stanley Aronowitz Reads The N.Y. Times - unedited master, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0047)
    - Michele Gibbs Reads Free West Indian, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0048)
      Michele Gibbs Reads The Free West Indian: Inside Grenada
      Michele Gibbs analyzes Grenada's national newspaper, The Free West Indian.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #40
    - Richie Perez on Fort Apache - Master, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0049)
      Richie Perez Watches "Fort Apache: The Bronx"
      Ritchie Pérez gives an in-depth look at the campaign to counteract the negative depictions of Puerto Rican and Blacks in the film Fort Apache: The Bronx. The campaign, as described by Pérez, proved that it is possible to have a unified, collective action against media racism. A clear description of the media's power to amplify and perpetuate harmful stereotypes is followed by an overview of the movie industry, and how the increasing media conglomeration is connected to banks and to the cable industry. Pérez gives an overview of the tactics that were used in the campaign, including boycotts, breaking media blackouts to get media attention, garnering a broad cross section of multi-cultural support, targeting key players and most importantly creating the context in which media needs to be judged by individuals in the public for racism, sexism and classism.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #42
    - Sandinista TV part I, 1983 (Box 121, Media ID: 276.0050)
      Sandinista TV News from Nicaragua Part I: "Peliculas a Las Once "
      In this rebroadcast of a Sandinista news report from Nicaragua, American viewers are offered a perspective about the proxy war between the Contras and the Sandinistas. Entirely in Spanish and without subtitles.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #43
    - Peter Rosset Reads News In Nicaragua - Master, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0051)
      Peter Rossett and Others Read: The Nicaraguan Press: Extra, Extra...
      Rossett is an agronomist and editor of the Nicaraguan Reader.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #44
    - Peter Hall Consoles at the AT&T Breakup - Master, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0052)
      Peter Hall Consoles at the AT&T Break-Up
      Peter Hall has written for Financial World, the Village Voice and other publications.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #45
    - Peter Hall Reads AT&T Breakup - Master, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0053)
    - Artists' Call On Central America - Master, 1984 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0054)
      Artists' Call to Central America: Lucy Lippard and Art for a Cause
      This show documents "Artists' Call Against U.S. Intervention in Central America", a two week benefit festival of performance art held in January of 1984. The event was curated and organized by Lucy Lippard and along with performance art, it showcased exhibitions, poetry readings, and experimental film and video. The program features an interview with Lippard as well as highlights from the event including performances by Lenora Champagne, Jerry Allen and the Smith Brothers. 1984 TRT: minute #46
    - Bill Boddy Reads 1934 Communications Act - Master #1, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0055)
      Bill Boddy Reminds The FCC of the 1934 Communications Act
      Bill Boddy is the author of a book about 1950's television.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #47
    - Bill Boddy Reads 1934 Communications Act - Master #2, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0056)
    - Bill Tabb Reads FORBES - Master, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0057)
      Bill Tabb Reads Forbes: Capitalist Fool
      Bill Tabb examines capitalism through the lens of the money magazine Forbes. Modeled around creator and owner of the magazine, Malcolm S. Forbes, Tabb believes that it serves as an advertisement for capitalism, shedding away the moral aspects of business in lieu of glorifying its sweet capitalist successes while simultaneously catering to and creating a network of business insiders, a separate sect of society who are celebrated for manipulating the public and investors into making them rich.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #48
    - Bill Tabb Reads FORBES - Live Master, 1983 / February 22, 1984 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0058)
    - Jim Rix Reads Organic Gardening - Master, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0059)
      Jim Rix Reads: Organic Gardening
      Jim Rix is a video engineer and organic gardener.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #49
    - Herb Schiller On The Selling Of New Technologies - Master, 1983 (Box 56, Media ID: 276.0060)
      Herb Schiller on the Selling of the New Technologies
      Herb Schiller critiques and questions the supposed benefits of the coming technological age. Schiller duly sheds light on the "computerization" of society, the merging of the academy, and the corporation and the equal potential for transcendence and failure that the computer age offers us all.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #50
    - Bob Edelman Reads Sovetski Sports - Master, 1983 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0061)
      Bob Edelman Reads: Sovietski Sport
      Bob Edelman is a sports writer and history professor.
      1983 TRT: 28 minutes #51
    - Gabor Ritterspoon Reads Pravda - Master, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0062)
      Gabor Ritterspoon Reads: Pravda
      Gabor Ritterspoon shows how important Pravda really was within Soviet society, not as a news and analytical source, but as a tool of propaganda and perhaps, more importantly, as the party's way of communicating and sending messages to the lower cadres and local burocrats. Ritterspoon shows that although the news never verbally clarified or included a negative message, those who knew how could unveil Moscow's realpolitik intrigue by reading between the lines.
      1984 TRT: 28 minutes #52
    - Patty Zimmerman Reads Variety - Master, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0063)
      Patty Zimmerman Reads Variety: Hooray for Hollywood?
      Patty Zimmerman gives a critical reading of Variety magazine.
      1984 TRT: 28 minutes #53
    - Pearl Bowser On Blacks in Film - Master, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0064)
      Pearl Bowser Looks at Early Black Cinema: The Legacy of Oscar Micheaux
      Pearl Bowser is the director of Chamba Educational Film Services, an archive of films, stills, and other memorabilia.
      1984 TRT: 28 minutes #54
    - Pearl Bowser On Blacks in Film - Incomplete Master, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0065)
    - Renee Tajima Reads Asian Images - Master, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0066)
      Renee Tajima Reads Asian Images in American Films: Charlie Chan Go Home
      This video traces the images of Asian women in Hollywood productions from Geisha Girls to Dragon Ladies. Renee Tajima argues that film and television help to promote the myth of Asian women as passive, thoughtless beings available for sexual consumption or as obedient servants.
      1984 TRT: minute #55
    - Patrick Esmond White Looks at TV Coverage of Mass Demonstrations - Master, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0067)
      Patrick Esmond-White on TV Demonstrations, 57 Mass Movements and the Media
      Patrick Esmond-White examines how the media's manipulation has deflated the power and influence of mass demonstrations. Filmed in Washington DC in front of the Lincoln Memorial, in the same spot that hosted one of most influential and inspiring mass demonstrations for peace and civil rights in 1963, Esmond-White compares the march of 1963 to marches of the present. He believes that the power of the demonstration as a political and social weapon has been defused through police regulation and media's portrayal the events; journalist frame demonstrations in a way that simplifies or leaves out the issues they're based on and portray demonstrators as unmotivated or unfocused. With the issues unspoken and the participants pacified, this media domestication creates an inaccurate and un-empowered viewpoint of American history and activism.
      1984 TRT: 28 minutes #57
    - Patrick Esmond White On TV Coverage of Mass Demonstrations - Master, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0068)
    - Eva Cockroft Reads Art Forum - Master, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0069)
      Eva Cockcroft Reads Art Forum: Art and Language and Money
      Eva Cockcroft looks through the pages of Art Forum and critiques the language used and its ability to communicate the ongoings of the art world with the masses.
      1984 TRT: 28 minutes #58
    - Nolan Bowie Reads About Privacy, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0070)
      Nolan Bowie on High Tech Snooping: The Government Shares the Deadbeat Dad List
      Nolan Bowie teaches communications at Temple University in Philadelphia.
      1984 TRT: 28 minutes #59
    - Eric Mankin Reads The L.A. Times - Master Edit, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0071)
      Eric Mankin Reads The LA Times, Paper Tiger West Pumps Iron at Gold's Gym
      Eric Mankin is a freelance journalist in Los Angeles.
      1984 TRT: 28 minutes #60
    - Varda Burstyn Reads Playboy - Master, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0072)
      Varda Burstyn Reads Playboy: Doing the Bunny Hop the All-American Way
      Varda Burstyn hosts a Canadian radio program called "Public Sex" and is the author of the book "Women Against Censorship."
      1984 TRT: 28 minutes #61
    - Jack Spence & Judy Butler Read La Prensa - Master, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0073)
      Judy Butler and Jack Spence Read Nicaragua's "La Prensa"
      Judy Butler, former editor of NACLA, has lived in Nicaragua since 1984. Jack Spence teaches at the University of Massachusetts.
      1984 TRT: 28 minutes #63
    - The Making of Far From Poland - Master, 1984 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0074)
      The Making of Far From Poland with Mark Magill and Jill Godmillow
      Mark Magill discusses the making of Jill Godmillow's 1984 documentary about Poland's Solidarity movement, Far From Poland, with the documentarian herself.
      1984 TRT: 28 minutes #64
    - The Day After - Nancy Peckenham on the Nicaraguan Elections, 1985 (Box 57, Media ID: 276.0075)
      Nancy Peckenham Reads The U.S. Press on Nicaragua: The Credibility of Cratologists
      Nancy Peckenham shows the ways the American press was biased during the 1984 Nicaraguan general election.She explains that the U.S. Newspapers and Reagan administration often gave contradictory and inaccurate information regarding the U.S. backing the opposition's freedom to run in the election and generally dismissed the Sandinista government's democratic values. Footage from Nicaragua's state TV shows otherwise, as each of the oppositional parties had it's electoral campaign broadcast on Sandinista Television.
      1985 TRT: 28 minutes #65
    - Kathleen Hulser Reads Subway Ads - Master, 1985 (Box 58, Media ID: 276.0076)
      F U CN RD THIS SBWY AD: Kathleen Hulser Takes the A Train
      Kathleen Hulser gives a critical reading of subway ads.
      1985 TRT: 28 minutes #67
    - Kathleen Hulser Reads Subway Ads - Dubmaster, 1985 (Box 58, Media ID: 276.0077)
    - Survey of Radical Periodicals with John Demeter & Tess Ewing - Master, 1985 (Box 121, Media ID: 276.0078)
      John Demeter and Tess Ewing Read Radical Periodicals: From "Against the Current" to "Yellow Silk"